Guide to the Robert E. Treuhaft Papers TAM.664
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Legal Case Files
  - Olsen, Arthur (IAC & 3rd Party Claim), 1968 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Painter, Harold for Mark Painter vs. Dwight & Margaret Bannister (child custody), 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Scheer, Robert "(Berkeley Bust)", 1972 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Segal [sic], Dan (Siegel, Dan), 1969 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Siegel, Dan - People v., 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    Includes transcript of audiotape recorded of Siegel speaking at an April 15, 1970 rally.
    Separated Materials
    1/4" reel to reel audiotapes of Siegel speaking at an April 15, 1970 rally were removed and housed separately for conservation purposes in an oversized box.
  - Siegel, Dan - Reel to Reel Audiotapes of Speech at Rally, circa Apr 15, 1970 (Box 6 (oversized), Folder 1)
    The larger of two tapes is labeled, "Tape of Dan Siegel Rotcy rally ..." "Rotcy" may signify ROTC (Reserve Officers' Training Corps).
    Access Restrictions
    Researchers interested in using audio materials in this collection must use a digitized copy, which we refer to as an access copy. The orginal media are not available for playback because of preservation concerns.
  - Slaughter, Arlene v. Berkeley Realty, 1964-1967 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Spring Mobilization, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Stender, Faye (contempt of court), 1973 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Strong, Barry Stephen, 1971-1973 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Treuhaft, Robert E. - Margolis "Trust" File, 1960-1966 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Treuhaft, Robert - People v. (re Free Speech Movement), 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Workers' Compensation Cases, 1994-1996 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Miscellaneous
  Postcards, leaflets, newspaper clippings.
  - Miscellaneous, 1962-2001, undated (Box 6 (oversized), Folder 3)
- Organizations
  This series focuses on organizations that Treuhaft worked in or for was a leader in. Their broad range reflect the broad range of his interests and involvement in public and professional life and politics, from the Civil Rights Congress (racial discrimination and the Communist Party), to the National Lawyers Guild (professional legal and social issues), to the International Association of Democratic Lawyers (international human rights) and the Consumers Co-Operative of Berkeley (community service) to his appointment to the California State Board of Funeral Directors and Embalmers (a direct result of his research for and association with Mitford's expose of the funeral industry in The American Way of Death).
  - California Board of Legal Specialization - Certificates and Related Materials, 1995-1996 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - California State Board of Funeral Directors and Embalmers - Minutes, Memoranda, Reports, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - California State Board of Funeral Directors and Embalmers - Newspaper Clippings, Articles, Brief, 1965-1989 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Civil Rights Congress, 1945-1971, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Consumers' Cooperative of Berkeley (Berkeley Co-op) Election Campaign - Correspondence, Leaflets, Documents, 1963-1969, undated; Consumers Cooperative of Berkeley (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Cooperative League of America - CIA Controversy, 1965-1973, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Free Speech Movement (University of California, Berkeley) - Student Leaflets and Publications, 1964-1965 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Free Speech Movement (University of California, Berkeley) - Newspaper Clippings and Articles, 1964-1965 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Free Speech Movement (University of California, Berkeley) - Newspaper Clippings and Articles (Retrospective), 1980, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - International Association of Democratic Lawyers (IADL) – Annual Convention - Documents, Correspondence, Reports, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - International Association of Democratic Lawyers (IADL) – Mission of Inquiry to Okinawa, 1972, 1989, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - International Association of Democratic Lawyers (IADL) – Mission of Inquiry to Okinawa - Newspaper Clippings and Publications Re, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - International Association of Democratic Lawyers (IADL) – Mission of Inquiry to Okinawa - Newspaper Clippings and Publications Re, 1970, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - International Association of Democratic Lawyers (IADL) – Mission of Inquiry to Okinawa - Notes, Correspondence, Reports from Trip, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - International Association of Democratic Lawyers (IADL) – Mission of Inquiry to Okinawa - Research Documents for - Collection of Published Legislation of United States High Commissioner of Ryukyu Islands, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - International Association of Democratic Lawyers (IADL) – Mission of Inquiry to Okinawa - Research Documents for - "Ryukyu Islands Fact Book" Publication of Department of the Army - United States Civil Administration of the Ryukyu Islands, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - International Association of Democratic Lawyers (IADL) - Mission of Inquiry to Portugal, 1964-1966 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - National Lawyers Guild, 1968,1985 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Political Issues/Activism, 1962-1989
  Subject files on these issues containing newspaper clippings and leaflets.
  - Cuba Missile Crisis, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Nuclear Disarmament, circa 1960s (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - People's Park - 20th Anniversary, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Vietnam War - Petition Against (reprints of one published in San Francisco Chronicle), 1964 (Box 6 (oversized), Folder 4)
  - Vietnam War, 1965-1966 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Research, 1961-1996
  Documents in this series include some of the research materials gathered by Treuhaft while working with Mitford on The American Way of Death, and for her expose of "The Famous Writers School."
  - Bowline (formerly "Famous Writers"), 1980, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Collector's Guild, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Famous Writers School (following publication of July 1970 article on), 1961-1972 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Funerals, 1963-1965 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Writings
  This series includes speeches and articles--published and unpublished--written by Robert Treuhaft. The files of poetry mostly consist of humorous rhyming doggerel written by Treuhaft and Mitford (either in tandem or separately) or on occasion by their friends (including poets and writers like Lawrence Ferlinghetti and Paul Jarrico), produced for particular private celebrations like birthdays, anniversaries, and parties, and replete with topical and political as well as personal and biographical references. Also included is an internal Communist Party document--a short resolution drafted by Jessica Mitford and submitted to the National Board of the Communist Party of the United States (CPUSA) on behalf of the Twin Peaks Club, a Bay Area branch of the CPUSA.
  - "The Academy and the First Amendment" (speech) - Manuscript, Clippings, Correspondence, Research Materials, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - "Criticism of the National Board: Resolution and Some Proposed Changes" (by Decca Treuhaft on behalf of Twin Peaks Club, California Communist Party), circa 1944 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - "From a Seat on California's Board of Funeral Directors and Embalmers" - Manuscripts, Correspondence, Clippings(for unpublished article for New York Times), 1976-1978 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - "Debtors' Rights and Remedies" (published in California Family Lawyer), 1962 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      No Subnote Content
  - "Naming Namers: A Reunion to Remember" (published in The Nation), 1984 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Poetry, 1958-1990, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Poetry, 1974; undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Poetry, 1965-1996 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Wills, 1966-1999; 1970-1985 (Box 7)
  Arrangement
  The files are arranged alphabetically by client last name.
  While the testaments in this series include those of some family members and friends and a sprinkling were drafted for people with public profiles (such as Mario Savio and writer Kay Boyle), most of them were drawn up for purely private individuals. These wills illustrate that in even his "non-political" work, Treuhaft was consistent in his commitment to representing individuals from underserved groups and ordinary people of modest means, including members of Oakland's African-American community, where Treuhaft had a strong client base as a result of his well-known work as a civil rights attorney.